Guide to the International Monitor Institute. Rwanda Videotapes and Audiotapes, 1992-1999 RL.00607
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
International Monitor Institute. Rwanda Videotapes and audiotapes
1992-1999
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
International Monitor Institute
RL.00607
4 Linear Feet
7 Gigabytes
The non-profit agency International Monitor Institute (IMI) operated between 1993 and 2003, primarily to assist international war-crimes tribunals by collecting, indexing and organizing visual evidence of violations of international human rights law. The International Monitor Institute Records, Rwanda Videotapes and Audiotapes span the dates 1992-1999, and comprise audiovisual materials related to IMI's documentation of contemporary conflicts and human rights violations in Rwanda. The collection contains videotape segments of news broadcasts as well as documentaries of the Rwandan genocide, including footage of massacre sites and refugee camps, and interviews with both victims and perpetrators of the genocide. The collection also contains audiotapes of broadcasts from Radio Télévision Libres des Milles Collines (RTLM) and Radio Rwanda, classified as incitement to genocide, as well as several recordings produced by Reporters without Borders. The bulk of materials in this collection are audiotapes of RTLM broadcasts.
About 335 items 7.04 GB
Access Restrictions
Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The International Monitor Institute. Rwanda Videotapes and Audiotapes were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2006-2007.
Biographical Note for Pippa Scott
The International Monitor Institute (IMI) was founded in 1993 by actress and film producer Pippa Scott. Scott, daughter of screenwriter Allan Scott who wrote some of the Astaire-Rogers films, was educated in California and in England, at Radcliffe College and the Southern California Institute of Architecture. Ms. Scott acted in such films as "The Searchers" and "Auntie Mame," and was a founding partner of the Emmy-award winning television company Lorimar Productions (producer of such TV hits as "The Waltons" and "Dallas" ). Scott established Linden Productions in 1987 to develop documentaries focusing on current issues. Linden's latest production is "King Leopold's Ghost," a documentary about the exploitation of the Congo by King Leopold II of Belgium. Scott was a member of the Women's Refugee Commission, the Pacific Council on Foreign Relations, and the Los Angeles World Affairs Council.
Historical Note for the International Monitor Institute
Organizational History. The International Monitor Institute was founded in 1993 and operated until 2003. Its primary mission was to assist international war-crimes tribunals by collecting, indexing and organizing visual evidence of violations of international human rights law. Videos and audio tapes were acquired through donation as well as on collecting trips by IMI associates in the former Yugoslavia, Kuwait, Rwanda, Sierra Leone, Iraq, Burma (Myanmar), Thailand, Cambodia, and other countries. IMI's activities also included developing regional archives of videos on conflict and human rights abuses, producing film and multimedia projects to assist humanitarian organizations, organizing public outreach events, conducting video research for governments, film makers, authors, and students, and providing educational outreach. Patrons and partners of IMI and its collections included the International Criminal Court and its staff, Human Rights Watch, Physicians for Human Rights, the Simon Wiesenthal Center, the governments of Bosnia-Herzegovina and Croatia, and former First Lady Hillary Clinton.
Collection Overview
The Rwanda Videotapes and Audiotapes section of the International Monitor Institute records contains descriptions of 47 tapes and 282 audiotapes collected by IMI that depict human rights issues and themes in Rwanda. These materials span the years 1992-1999. The videotapes largely document massacre sites and mass graves, evacuations, the role of missionaries and human rights activists, and conditions in refugee camps holding both victims and killers. Several documentaries and news reports examine the development of a genocidal ideology in Rwanda tied to its colonial past, as well as offer histories of Tutsi/Hutu animosity, including the role of the Belgian colonial government, France, and the Catholic Church. Many of the materials in this collection offer an analysis of government structure and politics in Rwanda before and after the genocide. In addition, this collection includes various news segments reporting on the movements of the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF) and the Rwanda Army as well as the effectiveness of the United Nations in the conflict; includes a documentary on Belgian soldiers killed in Rwanda.
The majority of audiotapes in this collection are RTLM and Radio Rwanda broadcasts inciting violence and orchestrating the genocide, encouraging youth to join military actions, and frequently referring to specific targets, such as Bilyogo and Nyamirambo. Broadcasts also include frequent reference to Inyenzi (cockroaches) and Inkotani (Tutsi Rebel Army). Many of the RTLM broadcasters accuse the Rwanda Patriotic Front (RPF) of the assassination of President Habiyarimana and argue that the Inkotani want to exterminate Hutus and so they must, in turn, be exterminated. Broadcasters speak out against French intervention and accuse the Belgians of alignment with the Rebel Army. The remaining audiotapes were produced by Reporters without Borders (RSF).
The majority of the materials in this collection are in French and Kinyarwanda. Both documentaries and news reports take the form of interviews with Rwandans about the massacres and interviews with members of the RPF as well as with figures involved with organizing the killings. The collection includes interviews with notable figures, such as Théoneste Bagosora on his role in the genocide, Ferdinand Nahimana, the former director of Radio Télévision Libre des Mille Collines (RTLM) about his failure to stop broadcasts that fueled the genocide, as well as accounts given by members of the death squad.
The series in this collection include the Rwanda Videotapes Series, the Rwanda Audiotapes Series (Audiocassette), and the Rwanda Audiotapes Series (Electronic Records). The bulk of the material for this collection belongs to the Audiotapes Series. Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive. Further material from the IMI Rwanda records can be found in IMI's organizational records, including printed transcripts of many of the audiotapes. All videotapes in this collection are in Betacam SP format. Please note that the descriptions of the tapes in this collection are based on IMI's data and were not originally drafted by Rubenstein Library Staff. Further organizational material on Rwanda can be found in the International Monitor Institute Records, also at the Rubenstein Library.
Collection Arrangement
Tapes are arranged in numerical order by Tape ID, a unique identifier assigned by IMI at the time they cataloged the tapes. Included is an RTLM number presumably assigned by the International Criminal Tribunal for Rwanda (ICTR).
Related Material
International Monitor Institute Records,1986-2006
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
International Monitor Institute. Burma videotapes, circa 1990-2002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
HU OSA 350, Fonds 350: Records of the International Monitor Institute
Open Society Archives, Central European University
Hutu (African people) -- Rwanda -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Genocide -- Rwanda; Death squads -- Rwanda; Videocassettes; Audiocassettes; Tutsi (African people) -- Crimes against -- Rwanda -- History -- 20th century; Rwanda -- Politics and government -- 1994-; Rwanda -- Colonization; Rwanda -- Church history; Refugee camps -- Rwanda; Massacres -- Organization; UNAMIR II (Rwanda); Radio-Télévision Libre des Mille Collines; International Criminal Tribunal for Rwanda; Human Rights Archive (Duke University); Habyarimana, Juvénal -- Assassination; Catholic Church -- Rwanda
- Rwanda Videotapes Series, 1992-1999, 5 boxes
  Conditions Governing Access note
  RESTRICTED: Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
  - Kirche Ohne Gewissen (A Church Without a Conscience), VHS [TRT 00:25:00] (Box 116, Video-cassette RW001)
    Scope and Contents note
    Air Date: 1996 Aug. 15
    Producer: Koos Barten
    Original Language: French, Kinyarwanda
    This report begins with Rwandans being interviewed at a grave site and follows with churches being accused of not showing a strong moral conscience, as well as denying any responsibility. An interview is featured with a Tai Chi professor, showing how he works to instill in the minds of Rwandans the 4 qualities of Tai Chi discipline: softness, humility, realism and patience. A close-up of a classroom follows, where Rwandans are learning self-discipline and self-control. It is believed that had the Rwandans taught self-control, the massacres would not have happened. The program focuses on Tai Chi training as a method to help heal the ills of the society and prevent future killing.
  - Sky News: Africa Bureau - Kigali, VHS [TRT 00:11:34] (Box 116, Video-cassette RW002)
    Air Date: 1996 Aug. 23
    Producer: Sky News Africa Bureau
    Original Language: English, Kinyarwanda
    Evacuation in Kigali: CBS reporter James Forlong reports for Sky New from Kigali, Rwanda about the UN controlled evacuation of the St. Famille orphanage in Kigali in late June, 1994. Based on a list, 200 out of thousands of Tutsis were allowed in the UN trucks, the rest remaining in the control of the Interhamwe, a Hutu paramilitary organization. Investigator: Faria Rekkas.
    Church Massacre: Church massacre at Ntarma, Rwanda in late June 1994. The report contains images of the aftermath of the massacre and an interview with a member of the Rwanda Patriotic Front (RPF) who claims the killings were the work of the Hutu paramilitary organization Interhamwe. Investigator: Faria Rekkas
    Kigali Prison: James Forlong reports for Sky News from Kigali, Rwanda about the living conditions in the Kigali prison where both victims and perpetrators are being held. Investigator: Faria Rekkas.
  - BBC News: Journey Into Darkness, 1994, VHS [TRT 00:38:11] (Box 116, Video-cassette RW003)
    Air Date: 1996 Aug. 30
    Producer: BBC
    Original Language: Kinyarwanda, French/Subtitles: English
    This broadcast is from April, 1994, as the war in Rwanda is in full scale. Fergal Keane of the BBC reports on how innocent civilians have been caught between Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF) and Rwandan Government soldiers' conflicts throughout Rwanda. Keane states that mass killings have been taking place in Kigali. Continuing his journey into the heart of the war, the reporter visits a Catholic church in the Nyarubuye region, the site of a mass killing. After venturing to Nyarubuye, the broadcast follows Keane into a refugee camp in Tanzania, where he meets with Gacumbitsi, the man accused of organizing the Nyarubuye massacre. He then moves on to Butare, where he focuses on the prefect Sylvan Nsabimana. Keane interviews Nsabimana, showing how he has protected people from being killed by government soldiers and militias before his being sacked and replaced by a Rwandan government army officer.
    - Digital preservation and use files (Digital-materials RL00607-SET-0002, Video-file RL00607-VHS-RW003.mov, Video-file RL00607-VHS-RW003.mp4)
  - Sitting on a Volcano (1st vol. in the 3-part Rwanda series), VHS [TRT 55:10:00] (Box 116, Video-cassette RW004)
    Air Date: 1996 Aug. 16
    Producer: Luc Cote
    Original Language: English, Kinyarwanda, French/Subtitles: English
    "Sitting on a Volcano" is the first in a three-part series on Rwanda by independent reporters Daniele Lacourse and Yvan Patry. In this report, Lacourse and Patry trace the exodus of Hutus who fled Rwanda to take refuge in neighboring countries. The reporters discuss the difficulties of life in the refugee camps, focusing on camps in the Democratic Republic of Congo near Goma, where thousands are falling victim to daily violence and disease. UN officials Chris Janowski, Guy De Tousignant and Luc Andre Racineare are interviewed. The report also focuses on assurances by the Rwandan government that it is safe for refugees to return home. "Sitting on a Volcano" criticizes the international community for continuing to feed the killers in these refugee camps outside of Rwanda while failing to acknowledge grave human rights violations in Rwanda. The report concludes by making the case that until those responsible for the genocide are brought to justice, Rwanda cannot begin to heal itself.
  - Bloody Tricolour, VHS [TRT 00:50:49] (Box 116, Video-cassette RW005)
    Producer: Yvan Patry, Sam Grana (NFB)
    Original Language: English, French, Kinyarwanda/Voice-over: English
    This video focuses on the murder of two Canadian missionaries, killed for having protested against corruption and human rights violations. The first of the two, Brother François Cardinal, worked at the controversial Rwanda College of Rambura, funded by the Canadian government and located in President Habyarimana's hometown. The report shows how Brother Cardinal was shot after charging that Canadian aid money was being diverted to the Rwandan president's advisors. The report also points out that Brother Cardinal's killers were never found. The second Canadian missionary featured on this video is Father Claude Simard, the only Canadian to have stayed in Rwanda during the genocide. Father Simard was murdered in 1994, after the genocidal regime had been overthrown by the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF). The report discusses how Father Simard risked his life to rescue Tutsis and speculates that his killers were Hutus acting to prevent Father Simard's testimony. However, the video goes on to reveal that Father Simard had made enemies within the current RPF regime by speaking out against reprisal killings against the Hutus. The investigation carried out by this team of journalists also raises some disturbing questions about Canada's own role in the Rwandan genocide.
  - La Part de Dieu, la Part du Diable, VHS [TRT 00:50:00] (2 copies (Box 116, Video-cassette RW006)
    Air Date: 1996
    Producer: Alter-Ciné, Telefilm Canada
    Original Language: English, French, Kinyarwanda/Subtitles: English, French
    Record No. 5 is an English version of this one.
    The second volume of the three-part film series on Rwanda investigates Rwanda's colonial past and explores Canada's role in the development of the genocidal ideology that started taking shape in the early 1960s when the country gained its independence and Belgian missionaries fled the country. The film tells the story of Father Claude Simard who was murdered in October 1994 in the Rwandan village of Ruyenzi and Brother François Cardoma(Brothers of Christian Instruction, a lay Catholic order), who was assassinated in Kigali by a six-person commando squad. Besides interviews with victims of the genocide as well as perpetrators, the film features interviews with: Brother François Cardinal, Father Georges Henri Leveque, Christine Stewart (Canadian politician), Grégoire Kayibanda (the first elected President of the Republic of Rwanda), Ltd. Celestin Kayitenkule, Capt. Tim Leesberg (Canadian United Nations Assistant Mission in Rwanda [UNAMIR]), Major General Guy De Tousignant (Commander UNAMIR), Paul Kagame (Former Minister of Defense and Former Vice-President of Rwanda), and Ltd. Wilson Gamesirire.
  - Pris au Piège, VHS [TRT 01:01:27] (Box 116, Video-cassette RW007)
    Air Date: [not available]
    Producer: [not available]
    "Sitting on a Volcano" is the first in a three-part series on Rwanda by independent reporters Daniele Lacourse and Yvan Patry. In this report, Lacourse and Patry trace the exodus of Hutus who fled Rwanda to take refuge in neighboring countries. The reporters discuss the difficulties of life in the refugee camps, focusing on camps in the Democratic Republic of Congo near Goma, where thousands are falling victim to daily violence and disease. United Nations officials Chris Janowski, Guy De Tousignant and Luc Andre Racineare are interviewed. The report also focuses on assurances by the Rwandan government that it is safe for refugees to return home. "Sitting on a Volcano" criticizes the international community for continuing to feed the killers in these refugee camps outside of Rwanda while failing to acknowledge grave human rights violations in Rwanda. The report concludes by making the case that until those responsible for the genocide are brought to justice, Rwanda cannot begin to heal itself.
  - Cursed Be Closed Eyes, VHS [TRT 00:37:49] (Box 116, Video-cassette RW008)
    Air Date: 1996 Aug. 22
    Producer: BBC: Giselle Fortenier
    Original Language: English, French
    This video features Françoise Saunier, an attorney with Doctors Without Borders, interviewing François-Xavier Nsanzuwera, the Rwandan Chief Prosecutor, and Joseph Matata, a human rights activist in Rwanda. Both Nsanzuwera and Matata discuss their disillusionment with the lack of intervention on the part of the international community in the face of the Rwandan genocide. Both of these individuals also focus on how they took it upon themselves to gather evidence that could help bring people responsible for the genocide to justice. Saunier seeks to show how the UN has yet to come any closer on delivering the justice promised to the Rwandans and the world. While Saunier visits the United Nations in New York and in the Hague, Mr. Matata completes his report in Belgium. François Xavier conducts interviews in Rwandan prisons, making sure there is sufficient evidence to convict, prosecute and start trials. At the time of this report, Doctors Without Borders and 42 other agencies had been ordered to leave Rwanda for political bias. The report also shows the International Tribunal's announcement of the first eight indictments for genocide. The report cites that no arrests have been made, however, and trials for those accused of genocide-related crimes in Rwanda have yet to take place.
  - Le Rwanda, au seuil du Multi-Partisme, VHS [TRT 00:56:00] (Box 116, Video-cassette RW009)
    Air Date: 1991
    The debate is taking place in Belgium in August 1991. The subject of the discussion is on the multiparty system. For a period of thirty years the Rwandan government operated under one party system (the Mouvement républicain national pour la démocratie et le développement [MRND]). On June 10th 1991 president Habyarimana declared a multiparty system. The focus in this debate is on the creation of a National Assembly, a process which was not provided in the constitution but reclaimed by opposition parties. In the debate there is a balance between Rwandan scholars and Belgian experts. The Habyarimana's government at that time of the debate was represented by Francois Ngarukiyintwari, Rwandan ambassador in Belgium.
  - Rwanda: Autopsie d'un Génocide, VHS [TRT 01:08:06] (Box 116, Video-cassette RW010)
    Air Date: 1996 Aug. 28
    Producer: Theophraste France3
    Original Language: Kinyarwanda
    The report begins with three people accused of genocide explaining that they were forced to commit their crimes. Their testimony is overlapped with footage of various atrocities. The camera then follows Madeleine, a Tutsi returning to Rwanda from France. The experience of the returning refugee is one of joy at being "back home" and one of sorrow upon learning who has died. Thérèse is another Tutsi who fled during the genocide and returns to find her home destroyed and her family dead. She confronts the sister of the man she believes led the attack against her family. The report then gives a brief history of Tutsi/Hutu animosity emphasizing the role of the Belgian colonial government and the Catholic Church. However, the report's main focus is on the role of the French government starting in 1975 which marks the first of several military pacts signed between the French and Habyarimana. Through a series of interviews and photos of signed documents the report builds a compelling case against the French. Mitterand, in particular, becomes quite involved in Rwanda's affairs and when the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF) launches its first invasion in October 1990, the French are there to halt their advance. The French mission is called NORWA and it does not call for direct involvement in the conflict. But several eyewitnesses as well as official Rwandan documents point to a French presence on the frontlines. The report then shifts its focus to the testimony of Janvier Afrika who alerted authorities to the existence of an organization within the government called Network Zero. Network Zero is purported to have carried out political assassinations and to have overseen the development of highly incendiary propagandist newspapers like Kangura. The documentary also points to the speech by Leon Mugesera in November of 1992, which along with Nahimana's creation of Radio Télévision Libre des Mille Collines (RTLM) in 1993 helped set the tone for the genocide. The report continues with a series of interviews of people like Bagosora and Hutu who have found refuge in the safety zone provided by the French in Operation Turquoise. Everyone maintains their innocence and blames the violence on the population's violent reaction to Habyarimana's death. The report does point out that the violence in the south, in Butare, did not begin until two weeks after the president's death. The documentary ends on the theme of justice. The chief prosecutor of Kigali points out the difficulties in prosecuting such a large number of accused. Indeed almost everyone is a victim or a perpetrator of genocide. Conditions in the Kigali prison are terrible and the process of bringing people to trial is very slow. The final question is whether genocide in Africa bears as much weight as one in Europe.
  - Bloody Tricolour, VHS [TRT 00:43:00] (Box 116, Video-cassette RW011)
    Air Date: 1996 Aug. 29
    Producer: David Harrison
    Original Language: English